At the Battle of the Somme
in World War I,
a NZ colonel led a formidable attack
on the German trenches that has
become legendary.
With death in the air, he advanced
on the enemy, despite being hit by
machine-gun fire.
Shot again and again, his body
shattered. He refused any help until
the Germans finally surrendered.
For having inspired his men
with his own contempt for danger,
this soldier was awarded the
greatest military honour of them
all - the Victoria Cross.
BELL TOLLS
The NZer was Lord Bernard Freyberg,
and his remains are buried in the
heart of the English countryside,
where today, family and friends are
meeting at a special commemorative
service for him.
Among the dignitaries, descendants
and attendants is a visiting member
of NZ's elite NZSAS -
Corporal Willie Apiata.
< You know Corporal Apiata?
Valerian Freyberg. How do you do?
Like the man he has travelled so far
to honour, Corporal Willie Apiata is
a holder of the Victoria Cross.
I never thought I would ever see
another NZer awarded one of that,
so...
In just a handful of weeks, the
award has propelled a soldier
used to a life of anonymity
into full public view,
making him the star of the NZ
military and a hero to his country.
The Victoria Cross - the result of
a selfless act of bravery in the war
in Afghanistan.
It was a moment long forgotten,
until just three months ago.
Captions by Able.
www.able.co.nz
Copyright Able 2016
At the headquarters of
NZ Special Air Service,
the commanding officer is about to
release the biggest story in the
unit's history -
one he has kept secret
for almost a year.
When I took over from my
predecessor, he informed me of a
number of issues,
and his parting shot was, 'Oh, and
by the way, you might wanna keep
your eye on this.'
In 2006, the colonel
was handed a dossier
recommending one of his corporals
receive the highest award for
gallantry, and, one month ago,
the recommendation was approved by
the head of the Commonwealth,
the Queen.
Do you wanna get Willie?
The mana of this honour makes
the story too big to hide,
so Corporal Willie Apiata must be
revealed to the NZ public tomorrow.
Hey, Willie. Let's go.
A five-year veteran of this unit,
Willie Apiata is oblivious to what
awaits.
It's usually bad news for a corporal
to be dragged into CO's office on
any day, let alone a Sunday morning.
Morning, Willie.
Boss.
Have a sit down.
Probably received the shock of
his life in the next five minutes.
Laid out in front of Willie
Apiata were three letters.
Just sorta wondering, you know,
'What the hell's going on here?'
Opened the first letter and
started reading through and...
yeah, it was... I was
quite speechless, actually.
Yeah. And emotional.
The Queen's representative - the
Governor-General - the NZ Prime
Minister and Minister of Defence
confirmed that Willie Apiata will
receive the rarest of military
honours,
making him one of just 12 holders
of the Victoria Cross alive in the
world.
Didn't really get a chance for it
to sink in. I was on the way down
to Wellington that afternoon.
As a Special Forces soldier,
the disclosure of Corporal Willie
Apiata's actions is unprecedented.
He's also the first person to
receive the Victoria Cross for NZ.
FLIGHT ANNOUNCEMENT
Willie is flying by his commanding
officer, his regimental sergeant
major and a mentor from the unit.
In Wellington, their job is to keep
Willie up close, but out of sight...
until tomorrow's announcement.
It's hard enough for me, knowing,
but I wasn't receiving the medal.
For Willie, it would be impossible
to sit on this secret, knowing that
his whole life was gonna change.
The first step in this life-changing
event takes the group to an almost
deserted NZ defence headquarters,
where the team responsible for
overseeing tomorrow's public
announcement has a long night ahead.
Hi, Clive.
Gidday, how are you? >
Clive Robinson. Willie Apiata.
Hi, Willie.
Clive will measure you for your
uniforms and then we'll get photos.
OK. Cool.
< All right.
Straight away, Willie is sent for
a uniform fitting in an adjacent
building.
One day, you'll have a
statue like this here.
The statue of Brigadier Bernard
Freyberg, VC, is a reminder to
Willie of his new-found status.
Look ahead, like you would. >
CAMERA SHUTTER CLICKS
Great. >
Your feet touched the ground yet? >
Drop your arms by your side.
Willie gets a new uniform befitting
the occasion of such an
announcement.
You know, Willie's more comfortable
in a pair of gumboots and a pair of
old trackies or his hunting gear.
The reality of it is that, you know,
that's not appropriate attire for a
public event.
It's all organised.
In the evening, Willie receives an
unexpected visit from the country's
most senior military commander,
Lieutenant General Jerry Mateparae.
From 10.30am tomorrow,
you'll be wearing those.
CAMERA SHUTTER CLICKS
Good luck.
WHISPERS: Thank you, sir.
See you tomorrow.
Understandably nervous, Willie
is the first NZ recipient of the
Victoria Cross in 64 years.
You've just gotta relax.
You'll get plenty of this.
It's a fairly daunting prospect to
know that you've gone from relative
anonymity
to becoming a public figure
for the rest of your life.
Three, two, one. Three, two, one.
CLICK! CLICK! CLICK!
OK, you can relax.
Willie gets a crash course in
how to be an overnight hero.
Willie's a very humble person by
nature and not prone to saying
too much.
But that doesn't cut the mustard
with an announcement like this.
Then people wanna know a little bit
about you and they wanna hear your
story.
You're a hero.
Absolutely. Now, you might need to
hear that a few more times before it
starts sitting comfortably,
and you're gonna hear it a lot.
As of tomorrow, when the first
radio bulletins go out, you are
a NZ celebrity. >
People worldwide will be reading the
Prime Minister's announcement and
seeing your photo by 11am tomorrow.
That's how big, how fast
it's all gonna happen. >
It's gonna take a little while
to rattle round in between your
ears, >
but I'm telling you now, bro,
it's the absolute reality. >
It's like how you jump into the deep
end of a pool and you can't really
swim, eh.
And you're treading so much water
trying to get back to the surface.
At midnight, the
call is made to stop.
We might tell them we're
there. 8am tomorrow?
For Willie, a sleepless night lies
ahead, as he knows that tomorrow,
NZ will be delivered the
groundbreaking news - they have a
new hero.
RADIO BULLETIN MUSIC PLAYS
Good morning. Welcome to Morning
Report on Radio NZ National.
It's the 2nd of July...
There hasn't been much sleep
for Corporal Willie Apiata
since the bombshell delivered by his
commanding officer yesterday that he
is to be awarded the Victoria Cross.
Today, it's NZ's turn to find out,
along with his family and his unit,
the NZSAS.
I'm still trying to get to grips
with what I've been awarded
and the roller-coaster
ride that had just started.
It's just before 8am and the NZSAS
soldiers head to Defence House in
preparation for the announcement.
For Willie, it's the last time he
will walk in public unrecognised.
It's cast a spotlight upon us
that we didn't necessarily want.
It's certainly cast a spotlight
on Willie. I'm sure he would've
preferred to remain anonymous.
The media briefing continues.
Because so many aspects of his
mission are deemed classified
or highly sensitive, there are many
no-go areas for what Willie can say.
< Did you shoot anyone?
It just set boundaries for Willie,
what he could say within the
bounds of operational security,
what he was comfortable with,
so that he had something to say.
It will be obvious that someone was
trying to shoot you and your mates,
and they'll want you to say it.
I'm thinking as a CO now. There are
realities. We are in Afghanistan.
You know, a number of NZers might
like the fact that Willie's received
a VC,
and there may be
some who aren't as...
Enthusiastic.
...aren't as enthusiastic, and
I'm very concerned about that.
Today's the big alligator.
One big alligator's gonna come.
I think one of the questions will
be, 'What are you feeling?'
'What does your family think?' >
Things like that. They just wanna
know you first, and, I think later
on, there'll be other alligators,
but with this big one, eh,
it's, 'Who is Willie Apiata?'
In the offices of the Minister
of Defence, aide Jeremy Seed
is putting the last
touches to the press packs.
The media have been called to a
special press conference by the
Prime Minister, starting in an hour.
Meet me at 10.30, OK? That's out
there. Nah, I'm not telling you any
more. OK. Cheers, mate. See ya.
They're all running around
like headless chickens- >
Oh, yeah. 'What's happening?'
Meanwhile, Willie succumbs to nerves
for the first time and steps out for
a break.
Countdown's getting closer, Sam.
We're doing something
the unit just doesn't do.
There's that public's... need and
right to know. It's already been
set out pretty clearly.
You know, we're not some
organisation that is particularly
comfortable -
feels this is necessary. We know
it's a requirement as a result of
the award,
but as far as I'm concerned,
it's business as usual.
The moment you say SAS, it tends to
draw publicity. I've never got my
head around that.
We just go about our business, but
SAS, by the nature of its business,
is a secretive organisation,
capable of very discreet operations.
And that draws public attention.
People like to know things that
they're not allowed to know.
September 11, 2001.
A series of devastating
attacks on US soil,
carried out by the terrorist
organisation Al Qaeda, shocked
the world.
Their network of training camps
was traced back to Afghanistan,
where, under the fundamentalist
Muslim army, the Taliban, they
operated with near impunity.
Within days of 9/11, US forces were
in Afghanistan and on the offensive.
Fire.
BOMB EXPLODES
Their aim - to overthrow the
Taliban, capture Al Qaeda operatives
and their leader, Osama bin Laden,
now the most wanted
man in the world.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
GUN FIRES
Much of Afghanistan quickly fell
under American control, but failure
to block all escape routes
meant bin Laden and hundreds of his
most hardened fighters had slipped
the net.
They were now hiding in
Afghanistan's remote mountain
regions.
An international coalition,
led by US forces, set out to
track the terrorists down.
Among those in relentless pursuit
was a small band of highly skilled
men from NZ's SAS unit -
a member of the world's
most renowned special forces.
Just hours ahead of his own press
conference, Willie undergoes a dress
rehearsal.
The camera's here on tripods.
Everyone will sit there with
their notebooks.
OK, Corporal. Can you tell us a
little bit about what actually
happened?
We've got it here on paper -
the description of the events
that led you getting this honour.
Nerves are shared by all as the
Minister and Chief of Defence make
final checks on the press release.
He took it remarkably well. >
He seemed quite composed.
Very composed. >
And relaxed about it.
Although apparently he's had
three cigarettes this morning.
< (LAUGHS)
How many people have you shot? >
That is the worst question to ask
a soldier. If you wanna insult him,
that's the best way to do it.
The carefully worded statement
gets some last-minute revisions.
CELL PHONE RINGS
Hello, Jeremy speaking. >
Adam. Adam!
Yeah? >
Drop your cup of tea. This is the
final statement. We're to get it
in as many packs as we can.
The men from Willie's squadron
gather at the unit and are the
first to hear the news.
I'm disappointed to not be here
in person, and the reason for that
will become clear very soon.
Today, I'm speaking to you about
something that, in my opinion,
is the biggest event in the
history of the 1st NZ Special
Air Service Group.
Hi, Jim speaking.
It's 10.30. All the boys will know.
Yep.
Big burden off your shoulders now. >
Oh, I know. Jeez. Crikey.
How long did you know about that? >
How long have I known about that?
Yeah.
10 months - since I took command.
The wonderful thing was that I saw
it in the CDF's office, and it was
passed to the CDF and then to me.
Signed by the Queen, and I
had a little moment myself.
So I had a small appreciation of
what it would be like for him to
open that letter.
He's earnt it. It's his. Doesn't
matter if he wants it or not.
He earnt it.
Along with Corporal
Willie Apiata's VC,
the Prime Minister announces three
other medals to be awarded for acts
of gallantry.
Morning, everyone. We're here
this morning to note that the
Governor-General
< has formally announced that the
Queen has approved four NZ Gallantry
Awards.
As the Prime Minister delivers
the news to the nation, Willie
is finally allowed to call home.
Corporal Apiata becomes the first
winner of the Victoria Cross for NZ
under the Royal Warrant for
the NZ Gallantry Awards of 1999.
RADIO: ...the Victoria Cross is
going to Corporal Bill Henry Apiata.
The Prime Minister says Corporal
Apiata showed stunning courage
by carrying an injured soldier
to safety while under fire.
In no time at all, the story
spreads across the media.
ONE NEWS INTRODUCTION PLAYS
TV: A member of the SAS has been
awarded the Victoria Cross,
making him the first NZer to receive
the award since the end of the
Second World War.
That's when it finally hit home, eh.
Seeing it announced to the world.
Corporal Apiata displayed
stunning courage and selflessness,
risking his life to save a
colleague in a situation of
extreme danger.
TV: That's Guyon Espiner, live.
In that small amount of time before
the press conference when it was
announced,
I was trying to get to grips with
all the things that were happening
to me.
Worried?
Until then, it had been all sort of
surreal. We'd talked about it, we'd
discussed how it was going to go,
but that's a whole different thing
when you see yourself on the
national news.
And for Willie Apiata,
it's a whole different thing
when you have to front up at your
own national press conference.