After only his second weekend off in
two months, Corporal Willie Apiata,
VC, is hard at work for the NZSAS.
BOMBS EXPLODE
GUNS FIRE
MEN SHOUT INDISTINCTLY
His time is a constant juggle
between the intense training
required of a Special Forces soldier
and the demands placed on
being the country's newest hero.
This calibre of this award is
something you can't hide, something
you couldn't keep under wraps.
Among a stream of invitations
Willie receives, one has great
personal significance.
It's from the 375 residents
of a tiny coastal community
in the Eastern Bay of Plenty
called Te Kaha, Willie's hometown.
They're very forthcoming and humble
people, and they really looked after
us when we moved there.
They teach you to value the land
where you live, appreciate what
you have.
Living down there is unspoilt and
hasn't been commercialised, as you
could say.
Up until now, Willie has been
supported by a close team,
personally led by his commanding
officer. But this weekend, that all
changes.
It wasn't about us. It wasn't about
the SAS. It was wider than that.
It was about Willie
Apiata and his iwi.
The homecoming at Te Kaha is
a trip Willie must take alone.
MAN CHANTS MAORI GREETING
The elders of this community have
pulled out all the stops, as the
population swells to nearly 4000,
making Willie's visit home the
biggest gathering of Maori in the
district in over a century.
WOMAN CHANTS KARANGA
It was a huge thing.
All those people
down there, you know.
It sort of took something like this
to really bring them all together.
ALL SING 'WHAKAARIA MAI'
Decreed a hui of national
significance, the homecoming is not
just to honour Willie.
You see all those photos of the
fallen soldiers. They're there
watching the occasion as well.
Soldiers like Lieutenant
Te Moana-Nui-a-Kiwa Ngarimu -
awarded the Victoria Cross,
but killed in action
during World War II.
You could feel in the air... at
every stage, you could feel our
ancestors.
You feel their presence.
ALL CONTINUE SINGING
'WHAKAARIA MAI'
Tomorrow will be the official
celebration, but tonight, a local
son is welcomed home.
Before the announcement of the
Victoria Cross, few knew Willie
was a soldier,
let alone a decorated member of
the country's elite fighting unit.
Welcome home, boy.
For them to find out like that,
I think they're still trying to get
over the shock of it, as well.
Really proud people.
The one-time mischievous kid has
returned a mature and much-loved
warrior hero.
Tena koe. We're proud
of you. So proud of you.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
A NZ Special Forces patrol in
Afghanistan was on the offensive
after being attacked in the early
hours of the morning by a large
number of insurgents.
For us, it was like a
blind hit from nowhere,
and it's a quick orientation to the
threat, which is what the guys did.
Despite his brush with death,
Corporal Willie Apiata threw
himself into the fray.
What I saw was Willie covered in
blood, wrapped up with a machine-gun
belt,
carrying a GPMG - General Purpose
Machine Gun - looking like he wanted
to do business.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
Started getting some fire back.
I honestly believed that they
bit off more than they could chew.
They'd stopped firing...
long before we did.
On Saturday morning, Willie Apiata
is formally welcomed on to the
marae,
and the emotion of the
occasion is overwhelming.
I didn't really realise the scale
the event was going to be until I
turned up that day.
WOMEN CHANT POWHIRI
Those people were so proud to have
me come back home. That will hang
with me forever.
Looking good, Wills. Looking good.
Wearing a precious cloak and seated
at the forefront of all dignitaries,
Willie receives a line-up of
speakers whose oratory represents
the feelings of the many guests.
(SPEAKS MAORI)
Emotions that I was feeling that
day,... there are no words for them.
Willie is called to the whare nui,
where he is handed a centuries-old
mere,
carved from the highest strike of
greenstone. Flanked by the images of
past generations of soldiers,
Willie turns and formally
acknowledges the people,
his tears barely kept in check.
CROWD CHANTS HAKA
Willie. Well done. Well done.
Welcome home.
Warrior to warrior, Willie now
greets the surviving war veterans.
Thank you for the honour.
Thank you for knowing you.
Their respect is such that the
sight of the Victoria Cross is
too much for some to bear.
I feel all the mana coming off
those men. They're so proud.
They're so honoured to be there.
It takes Willie several minutes
to make his way through the
well-wishers to the official dinner.
Can we move back? More space
to move straight through.
It must seem a long way for Willie,
from wherever it was in Afghanistan,
back home to be celebrated
for what he's done.
In government, we hear whenever our
people are involved in some kind of
action overseas.
Word comes back. 'There's been an
incident, an action.' Eventually,
we hear a bit more.
In this case, eventually, the Chief
of Defence came in and he said,
'Something extraordinary happened.'
We started documenting this story,
looking at the precedents, and,
on that basis,
I was advised to recommend to
Her Majesty the Queen that Corporal
Willie Apiata be recognised.
APPLAUSE
It wasn't just me there that day.
There was a lot of other men on the
ground.
And... we all know we are a tight
family and we just look after each
other,
and that's just the way we are.
There's an old saying, 'Who are
ye in rags and rotten shoes?
The bearded ones blocking the way.
'We are the pilgrims, master.' We're
just humble men - just ordinary
blokes, just like everybody here.
My heart goes out to everybody here.
Everyone. We are one. One Maori.
Tena koutou. Kia ora koutou katoa.
# Maori Battalion
march to victory,
staunch and true.
# Maori Battalion march to glory,
# take the honour of
the people with you.
# And we will march,
march, march to the enemy.
# And we will fight
right to the end. #
Passchendaele - out of the seasonal
mist unique to this corner of Europe
comes a line-up of Commonwealth war
veterans, high-ranking officials and
national leaders.
They have come from all over to
pay their respects at the
90th anniversary
of one of the bloodiest
conflicts of the First World War.
Passchendaele represents the
greatest loss of life to NZ
servicemen
in any battle or campaign or war
that NZers have ever been involved
in.
It exceeds Gallipoli in
terms of the loss of life.
It's extraordinary, and so many
NZers went to their death at
Passchendaele,
over literally several
hundred metres of dirt.
Among the NZ dignitaries is
Corporal Willie Apiata, VC.
Tremendously important, but Willie,
as our most recent VC winner -
the first since World War II -
was there for the country,
but also for Willie.
This day will prove a
significant turning point
in Willie's understanding of the
medal he now so proudly bears.
I felt very honoured, going over,
but, you know, I was seeking
knowledge at the same time.
When the official party arrives at
Tyne Cot, the largest Commonwealth
cemetery in the world,
the true sense of scale
and loss is felt by all.
This is an occasion to honour
and remember those
who made the supreme sacrifice
in the War to End all Wars.
# Hold thou thy cross
# before my closing eyes.
# Shine through the
gloom and point me to... #
With hundreds of NZers laid to rest
here, Tyne Cot has a profound effect
on Willie.
I saw the walls with all their names
on it. That's when it hits home -
that so many men just walked
out of their trench, eh,
and knew they were going to die.
# Abide with me. #
For the rest of the day, Willie
visits sites where thousands of
young men lost their lives.
The Kiwis took 20 minutes to get
out of the front line, get across
no-man's-land
and to the German front
line, so they moved fast.
The Germans knew where they were and
started to shell them. That's when
we took most of our casualties.
Almighty God, in whose hands
are the living and the dead.
We give you thanks for all your
servants who have laid down their
lives in service of our country.
Grant them your mercy in the
light of your presence. Amene.
CHURCH BELL TOLLS
Confronted with the huge loss of
life on an unprecedented scale at
Passchendaele,
Willie's own brush with death
now takes on a new meaning.
All the people I know that have
been awarded them are just ordinary
blokes, and that's all they are.
Just normal blokes just looking
out for their mates and doing what
people call extraordinary things.
It takes some time to sink in, but I
think Passchendaele was a watershed
time
for him to really understand,
now, what it was really all about.
Departing from their official
schedule, Willie returns to Tyne Cot
Cemetery, this time in private.
We went back to Tyne Cot, and that's
where, you know, I had my time.
Quite heavy on the
chest there, Willie.
WHISPERS: Jesus.
What were you doing at 21?
It's the first Kiwi
one we've seen, eh?
There's another one of the brothers.
It makes you feel quite unworthy,
walking amongst all those
gravestones,
knowing that they put more forward
than any man could ever ask of them.
As dusk falls, the two soldiers find
a grave with the familiar markings
of a Victoria Cross.
Tena koe, e hoa.
That's one of your brothers, mate.
Like so many other Victoria Cross
winners, Canadian Private JP
Robertson died on the battlefield.
It's a tribe that you've
been... basically awarded into.
And that's a forefather that's gone
before you, even though he's not a
Kiwi.
But it's someone that now- That
carried the burden that I have to
carry now.
It's four months since Corporal
Willie Apiata of the NZ
Special Air Service
was awarded the
Victoria Cross for valour,
and in that time he has come to
terms with the fact that he is now
a national hero
and the latest member of a
truly unique association of men.
Suddenly been automatically enlisted
into a club of very few members.
Accompanied by his commanding
officer, Willie has requested
a meeting with his lawyers.
Hi, Jim.
Nice to see you.
And you.
He has reached a momentous decision.
Thought long and hard about
what I wanna do with the medal.
Wasn't just earned by me. It was
earned by all those men that were
out there that day.
In simple terms, it seems to me that
you're giving away more than you've
ever had,
almost before you've got it.
It'll never be sold, or there will
never be any quarrels over it.
As you know, what this does is gift
the Victoria Cross, effectively, to
NZ.
Congratulations.
When my life has passed, my son, his
sons and our bloodline will be able
to wear it and represent me.
The resting place for it
will be here in the unit.