With the Prime Minister's
announcement that Corporal
Willie Apiata
has been awarded the Victoria Cross,
the 35-year-old soldier must now
face a national press conference.
And he's not looking forward to it.
From where I come
from, from the job I do,
even giving a little is too much.
And when you're ready, just start.
Lieutenant Colonel Mike Shatford
briefs the press on the rules.
I'd like to outline the process
that will happen today so we're
all clear on the rules of the game.
Corporal Apiata has only just
found out about this huge honour.
It is quite overwhelming,
so I would ask that you go as
easy as you possibly can on him.
Willie's moment of reckoning
cannot be delayed any longer.
I don't think anyone could prepare
themselves for what I walked into
that morning.
I'm right behind you.
Cheers, sir.
CAMERA SHUTTERS CLICK, APPLAUSE
Just standing there...
just unreal, eh.
Just real emotional.
Willie Apiata joins yet another
group of elite people.
This is the first award of
the Victoria Cross for NZ.
His is the first and the only
Victoria Cross to be awarded
to a NZ serviceman
since the end of the
Second World War.
The questioning quickly turns
to that night in Afghanistan.
Hey, I was doing my job, eh,
and just looking after my mates.
It was the...
What was going through
your mind at that time?
TENSE SILENCE
You can sense the
anticipation of the press
to get some information out of
you so they can tell your story.
'Where's my buddies?'
'How can I help them?'
During this incident, did you feel
fear? What was the feeling that went
through you as you were doing this?
Um...
At the time, I was just... doing
what I've been trained for. Doing my
job.
Look out for my mates.
Watch each other's back, and...
The heat of the moment.
I can't really say at this time.
There was a lot of fire going on.
You weren't worried about being hit?
< I think it's probably time to
take the questions somewhere else.
< Willie is quite overwhelmed by the
situation, and perhaps we can talk
more about other things.
Do you see yourself, perhaps, as the
living legend, as others might do
from this day forward?
I see myself as Willie Apiata.
I'm just an ordinary person and...
this is me.
This is one of the hardest things
I've ever had to do, actually.
Good one. All done.
Thank you, sir.
It was a great job.
Cheers, boss.
It was an enormous amount of
pressure on him to present himself.
I think he did a great job.
But Willie was just Willie. He was
just being himself. That is him.
That is Willie the man.
After facing the cameras, Willie
asked for a private moment with the
people who helped him through it.
I've always been a man of few
words, but I need to say something.
Since 9 o'clock yesterday, it's just
been an unbelievable experience.
The old 12 o'clock news today,
that sort of really hit home for me.
I'd just like to thank you all for
everything that you've done in the
last three years,
building up to this day.
I can't believe I only just found
out 9 o'clock yesterday about all of
this,
but thanks very much. I... Words
can't explain how much I appreciate
what you fellas have done.
Thank you. Kia ora.
APPLAUSE
You're gonna get sick of us.
Cheers, Willie.
Cheers.
BERNADINE OLIVER-KERBY: NZ has a
new living legend - a man who
displayed...
Back at the hotel, Willie watches
his story lead the national news for
the second time that day.
...hasn't changed me at all.
I'm still one of the boys, back at
work, and always will be.
Awesome.
Yeah.
63 media stories about Willie.
Online coverage through NZ spreading
to Australia, France, the UAE.
This is just an awesome...
thing that's happening.
I know. >
I didn't think it'd be
that big at all. But...
it just felt like it almost
went global, just like that.
Some messages of support for
Corporal Willie Apiata. From Snoop
in South Korea.
READS: It makes me proud
to be a Maori again.
From Sunny. (READS) Salaam, peace.
God bless you and your family for
the ultimate good deed you did.
Dean in Queensland. (READS)
'Kia ora, Willie. Well done, from
the bros in Iraq. Kia kaha, Deano.
'Nice one. If I see you in the
pub, it's my shout.' (CHUCKLES)
Hey, get that guy's name.
For those charged with
keeping the secret,
the public announcement of Willie's
Victoria Cross has gone off without
a hitch.
Cheers to you and the team.
The relief it was out there.
For me, it was a great relief
because I'd sat on it for some
10 months or so.
Suddenly, it wasn't a secret
that had to be kept any more.
In just a few hours, Corporal Willie
Apiata of the NZSAS has become an
official NZ hero.
But a reluctant one.
Before they announced it, I'd
finally sort of put it to rest.
But it's resting no more. It's gonna
be there now for the rest of my
life.
But, you know, you'll never forget
that night. It'll always be there.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
Following the 9/11 attacks, an
international coalition was on the
hunt for Al Qaeda in Afghanistan.
Among those pursuing the
terrorists were the NZSAS.
Renowned trackers, they're one of
the world's leading Special Forces.
Highly skilled, the NZers were able
to penetrate far behind enemy lines
in all environments.
They were ideally suited for
the rugged Afghanistan landscape.
BOOM!
Operating in small convoys of
motorcycle pathfinders and
armed patrol vehicles,
The NZSAS faced an elusive enemy
that had used the local terrain to
deadly effect
against the Russian
army years before.
Among those hand-picked for this
deadly mission was Corporal
Willie Apiata.
You have all these things that may
happen to you, but you resort to
the training that you've been given.
Moving through villages, the NZ
troops gathered intelligence on
any suspicious movements.
We're chasing information, and
information to us is currency.
Good information could lead
them directly to the enemy.
BOOM!
On this occasion, a cache of guns,
explosives and rocket-propelled
grenades were taken from the enemy.
But Corporal Willie Apiata's patrol
would not be so lucky on their next
encounter.
Their time in the capital has gone
to plan, and the commanding officer
and his team head back to base.
But changes in Willie's
life are apparent.
The first person to ask him for an
autograph sort of said, 'Would you
mind giving me an autograph?'
Willie said, 'Sure,' and looked at
me and wasn't quite sure what to do.
I've never been asked for one, so
it's new to me. I said, 'Well, just
put your name.'
So he did. He wrote
'Willie' and handed it back.
I said, 'We can do it better next
time.' So now he signs himself
'Willie Apiata, VC', as he should.
Corporal Willie Apiata returns to
base and back to the routine of a
Special Forces soldier. He hopes.
He was welcomed back, and it was
business as usual, as far as the
guys were concerned.
Handshakes - not too many
man hugs go on around this place.
Doesn't matter if he's wearing the
Victoria Cross on his chest.
If he does something wrong,
he's gonna know about it.
I was coming in every morning -
still do PT as usual every morning.
Get your feet back on the
ground working with the lads.
Doing some shooting, just getting a
bit of cordite back in the nostrils.
Getting your eye back in and
making sure you're still doing it.
GUN FIRES
Despite his attempts to return to
normality, everything has changed
for Willie Apiata.
He's the only corporal in the
NZ military with his own office.
He's only a corporal. He's got his
own office, but he's gotta answer
a couple of hundred emails
and letters every few days.
I don't think other corporals
around here would want to do that.
Messages have flooded in from
politicians, celebrities, sporting
heroes, war veterans
and other proud regiments from every
part of society and corner of the
globe.
You get a feel of how the
people are feeling out there.
The response from them was
awesome. It's just overwhelming.
It's been an interesting process. A
lot of people have asked for Willie
to go and speak or be at events.
I think a lot of people forget that
Willie's actually still a soldier
and he's a soldier in the SAS.
I'm trying to keep things
as normal as we can.
Trying to schedule events as best
we can to... not to disrupt him.
If possible, get him out
for a jump with the lads.
But Willie's newfound
status is now inescapable.
Even at work, a member of the flight
crew ambushes Willie for an
autograph
while he prepares for a training
jump with other members of the unit
and the troop.
Is that you? >
ENGINE ROARS
(SHOUTS)
A few brief moments of isolation
under canopy offer Willie his only
relief from the attention.
But there is one set of faces
that Willie is desperate to see.
My family's suffering at
the moment, eh.
But I know I've just gotta be
patient and I'll get that time
at home.
Over the next few days, media
interest intensifies on
Willie Apiata
and the actions in Afghanistan
that led to his Victoria Cross.
GUNS FIRE
Meanwhile, Willie learns the
financial and personal pressures
all VC winners must face.
I was concerned, as any commanding
officer would be, when one of his
subordinates is in this position.
I was concerned for him, personally.
While some recipients have succumbed
to the substantial dollar value of
the medals,
others have suffered a greater toll.
There are enough stories of Victoria
Cross winners that have ended up
destitute, or drunk and destitute.
We certainly didn't want that to
occur, and there's no inclination
that it's likely to, either.
After much demand, the media
are granted a series of closely
supervised one-on-one interviews.
All right. If you guys will follow
me. Well, welcome to the unit.
But the very private soldier is
still uncomfortable with his public
role.
I never thought I'd ever be
talking to the media about it. Yeah.
Hello.
With his famous corporal on edge,
the CO lets everyone know exactly
where the boundaries lie.
We're a discreet organisation.
We're not comfortable in the public
eye. It's not what we do naturally.
We're just trying to balance what NZ
needs from Willie and what Willie
needs.
Given that the SAS, you know, builds
its reputation on anonymity, isn't
that shot for him now?
No, not at all. He still has
anonymity with a gas mask on,
doesn't he?
The media are no longer covering
the story for just NZ but for news
agencies around the globe.
Last week, Willie Apiata
was this anonymous bloke...
...and now you're having to do all
these horrible interviews with us.
(LAUGHS) >
The public and NZ wanna know who
I am. It's a soldier in the NZSAS,
and that's who I am.
We've been receiving messages
on our website by the hundreds.
They generally wanted to know
who I was and how I was feeling.
Yeah, it's still quite an
overwhelming thing that I'm going
through.
And, you know, I'm taking
it one day at a time.
You've said you'd rather face
the Taliban than the media.
There's a couple of them, actually,
that were right up in your face,
but...
we all know they just want a piece
of Willie Apiata, so we had to give
them a little bit.
Put you in front of that and
take a photo as an honour.
They're big words you don't really
like. You were just doing your job.
(LAUGHS) OK, mate.
Um, so,... uh...
Some journalists go fishing for
more details about Afghanistan.
Now, Afghanistan. How long had
you been in Afghanistan when
this particular action happened?
Probably no questions in
terms of the specifics, sir.>
OK, then.
So, you were up against
a group of Taliban?
No specifics on that. >
(SIGHS) So, there's really no
more that you'd tell us about
Afghanistan?
Not the specifics. There's reasons
for that. We're not being defensive
or trying to hide anything.
In the hunt for Al Qaeda, Corporal
Willie Apiata's patrol travelled to
the remotest regions of Afghanistan.
We would go to villages
to talk to the locals.
In some places we'd go to,
they haven't seen soldiers
since the Russian days.
Biblical is the only
thing that springs to mind.
Donkeys, people carrying piles
of wood, mud huts. Very biblical.
There were occasions we'd get
flowers thrown on to our vehicle
cos they were happy to see us.
We're a different bunch, eh, as
Kiwis. We pretty much get on with
just about everybody.
But greetings weren't
always so enthusiastic.
We approached this village before
last light and thought, 'We'll visit
and let people know we're there.'
The welcoming we got from that
village was quite hostile - just
in the way that they looked at us.
We had been told, previously,
that the village was sympathetic
to Taliban.
With the meeting set up for the next
day, the patrol moved away from the
village to make camp for the night.
Some form of dominating ground that
we can fight from, that you feel
secure in,
that have got eyes on,
basically, all around the fence.
But the landscape failed to
offer an ideal location to lay up.
There was still a lot of
ground that we couldn't see into.
Hiding in the shadows, a
hostile army was amassing.
At the end of this first week,
Willie gets a much-needed short
break.
No media, celebrity
snapshots or personal minders.
I really needed it.
Just to clear my head.
Get my head around it and get
some closure with my family.
They hadn't seen me since
this thing started,
and they were starting to tear the
TV apart every time I was on.
Willie heads south to see his
partner and son and his biggest
follower.
Only my mum really understood
what it was about.
Once it had come out on the TV,
basically, the rest of my family
finally realised.
You know life's not the same any
more on the home front, don't you?
My mum's followed me through
my career ever since the first day
when I went away to do my
first weekend of army training.
Jeepers. I didn't
know you had all these.
Oh, that was when I
came back from Afghan, eh.
Mm.
After a few years in
the Territorial Army,
his mother would also see Willie's
disappointment after an unsuccessful
first attempt to join the NZSAS,
an old injury denying
his chance of selection.
I was pretty gutted about that, but
I had a good unit that I was with at
the time,
put me back into work and says,
'Hey, there will always be another
opportunity', and I knew that.
After serving in East Timor, Willie
tried for the NZSAS selection again
in 2001.
This time, he made the grade.
Holy Father, bless this food we're
about to devour. Bless this house.
Bless our journey. Amen.
As a combat trooper, Willie is away
on training and operations much of
the year,
so he spends all his remaining
time with his partner and son,
as they come to terms with
the changes in Willie's life.
Nowadays, no matter how tired I am
or how drained I feel, I'll always
make time to spend with my boy.
I know that's all he wants - to
be with Dad. He's away so much.
POIGNANT MUSIC
(LAUGHS)
Ah... we missed it.
That's the one. You're
reeling it up a little bit.
All too soon, Willie's weekend with
loved ones is over. Their next
meeting will be in Wellington,
where the Governor-General will
present Willie Apiata with the
Victoria Cross in a public ceremony.
POIGNANT MUSIC CONTINUES