The day has finally arrived for the
investiture of the Victoria Cross.
And Corporal Willie Apiata has been
joined by members of his family for
the monumental occasion.
It was really great that my family
could come down and experience that
with me.
It's the first time we ever
got all of my family on a plane.
My mum's never flown. My two
older sisters have never flown.
I wanna come with you.
You know Daddy'll be
there waiting for you, eh.
Give us a kiss. Eh?
Willie's journey to Government House
will take only 15 minutes, but it's
a day three years in the making.
The unit, at the time, raised a
recommendation and arrived at the
Chief of Defence Force's office.
The recommendation went to the
offices of the Prime Minister,
where previous awards were compared.
It was then pushed further,
to Buckingham Palace.
Dates, events and actions were
rigorously checked, double-checked
and checked again.
As such, they then recommended to
the Queen that maybe Willie should
be considered for a Victoria Cross.
In 1857, Queen Victoria awarded the
first Victoria Cross. Today, Willie
will receive a bronze medal cast
from the same cannon metal
dating back to the Crimean War.
Good luck, mate.
Thank you, sir.
It's all sort of
coming home to roost?
Yep. I'm there.
< Make no apologies, but...
(LAUGHS) Nah, it's no worries.
While other distinguished
guests arrive,
Willie catches up with other
personnel who will be decorated
for their acts of bravery.
We know what happened that day, and
no words really have to be spoken.
Good to see you, mate. How's
everything been? Are you managing?
Yeah. Managing, mate.
I thought you did a great job on TV.
I mean, it would have been bloody
shit...
I was in Australia and I saw him.
They had to tell you to shut up (!)
(LAUGHS)
Here you go, Daddy's
gonna put you down now, OK?
Yeah.
Cos you're heavy. You're a big boy.
I'm not a big boy. I'm a little boy.
Among those keen to greet Willie is
a former All Black captain and the
chief of the NZ Army.
Meanwhile, his mother
chats to a familiar face.
Usually when you come to Parliament,
no one's there and it's about
2 o'clock in the morning.
(LAUGHS)
As the press arrive at Government
House, a very private ceremony is
already taking place inside.
Ladies and gentlemen, Their
Excellencies the Honourable Anand
Satyanand and Mrs Susan Satyanand.
Three other medals are to be
awarded for acts of gallantry.
Each of you has, as members of the
1st NZ Special Air Service Group,
rendered distinguished
service to our country, NZ.
Quite often, a lot of our work is
not acknowledged, and nor should it
be.
But in this particular instance,
these individuals, representative
of the SAS group,
were being recognised and they had
the opportunity to be in a very
dignified way.
But the celebrations of today are a
far cry from the events of three
years ago.
During a tour of Afghanistan, an
NZSAS patrol was forced to lay up
for the night
in terrain that offered
limited defensive protection.
As the crew of Corporal
Willie Apiata's vehicle slept,
a small army of insurgents lay
under the cover of darkness
with rocket-propelled
grenades and machine guns.
If something's gonna happen, it'll
always happen when you least expect
it. And, hey. That's what happened.
BOMB EXPLODES
The whole car erupted,
basically, as the first RPG hit.
BOMB EXPLODES
I woke up standing up, with my
sleeping bag around my ankles.
Blown off the bonnet.
BOMB EXPLODES
You could feel all the over-pressure
coming off it, as well, plus all the
small arms in the background.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
I just crawled as low as
I could to the vehicle.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
The RPGs and machine-gun rounds
ripped through the vehicle
commander's arm.
I remember him looking for the entry
and exit and looking right through.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
The three of us were at the
back of the wagon, pinned down.
The whole wagon was shaking.
The bullets ripping
through the metal.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
RPG rounds hitting it after
that. One after the other.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
BOMB EXPLODES
I sort of lost count on how many
rockets, I suppose, hit the wagon.
I think I might have
counted about five or so.
With support nearly 100m away,
the vehicle commander was rapidly
bleeding to death.
I can remember my body going into
peripheral shutdown and I can
remember my feet...
losing feeling in my feet as
the blood drains to your core.
Imagine turning a tap or hose on,
and the water splashing on the
ground.
As the enemy approached, the
NZers faced certain death.
I don't think anyone could have come
to help us. We had to get ourselves
out.
The moment has finally arrived
for Willie to receive the
Victoria Cross.
All right. >
On your lead, my liege.
Good luck.
There are two caveats placed
on awarding the Victoria Cross.
The first is a singular brave act
or deed. Secondly, the nature of
that act must be such
that it turned the tide of the
battle that was being conducted.
I also read that you have to
have a 90% chance of dying.
PIANO PLAYS 'GOD SAVE THE QUEEN'
As Governor-General, I have the
authority and privilege on behalf
of Her Majesty the Queen >
to confer the honour of the
Victoria Cross for NZ >
on Corporal Bill Henry Apiata of
the NZ Special Air Service Group. >
You are the first person to
receive the Victoria Cross for NZ.
Corporal Bill Henry Apiata, NZ
Special Air Services, of Papakura.
Well done.
I'm very privileged to share
this special NZ moment with you.
You should wear it with great pride.
All the best to you.
Thank you, Your Excellency.
Tena koe.
When he pinned it on my chest, it
was like one of the heaviest things
I've ever carried, eh.
For such a small, small thing.
APPLAUSE
I felt very proud
that day, you know.
Things had finally sunk in by then,
and I just felt very proud for my
country.
Yeah, well, I've always been a man
of few words and I'm still trying
to get used to the press and that.
It's been a very emotional
and humbling experience today.
All the NZers out there that have
supported me and sent me all those
messages,
I'm still reading through them all
and I will read them all. They are
very heart-warming messages.
I've given up being
surprised by these guys.
Just when you think they're at the
level of their endurance or the
level of their capabilities,
they'll always come out with more,
so... In his particular instance,
he's done a fantastic job.
After a day surrounded by the
country's leaders, a proud family
gets a brief moment to themselves.
That is so precious.
Man, that's gonna be loaded by
the time you're finished...
(LAUGHS)
Hey, you're cutting the time, eh.
Yeah, no. I understand that.
You can say goodbye to them.
I love you, my brother.
Yeah, you look after yourself.
See you when you come home.
Love you.
Love you too, sis.
Cheers, boss. Thanks.
And then, at the end of the most
important day of his life, Willie
is finally alone.
I was just, like, be at peace with
myself for just those few moments.
You know, and take in
all the day's events.
Because even though it was the end
of the day, the journey wasn't over
yet.
If Corporal Willie Apiata thought
after receiving the Victoria Cross
he would quietly return to his
former life in the NZSAS, he was
mistaken.
The award brings great opportunity
and great privilege, but it also
brings tremendous responsibility.
Instead of resuming normal duties,
Willie and the Victoria Cross are
sent on a week-long publicity
road trip.
Everybody wanted to meet Willie,
wanted Willie to appear at events.
The launch pad for the tour is
Waiouru, the main training base
for the NZ Army.
Double march! Hup! Hup!
Already, the impact of Willie's
new celebrity status is apparent.
The corporal's accommodation is
upgraded to one normally reserved
for VIPs.
When the CO said, 'We're crashing at
the Homestead, I was like, 'Whoa.'
I'm a lieutenant colonel. I don't
stay at the Homestead. It's not the
place a corporal would stay.
Normally, you'd be
in the barracks there.
BOTH LAUGH
At Waiouru Military Museum, Willie
literally comes face to face with
his new-found fame.
It's been amazing, the amount
of public interest in here.
We've had a couple of panels down
there for about six months. Hardly
anyone notices.
This has been up since last week and
certainly, the interest in it's been
amazing.
All will be transferred
permanently down to the main museum.
That's the Falklands and the Gulf.
The museum is home to
NZ's Gallantry Awards.
All the Victoria Crosses that we
hold here, but obviously, all real.
This one's Charles Upham's.
Willie's actions have placed him
beside the likes of Charles Upham -
NZ's most famous double VC
winner - and Bernard Freyberg.
In these surroundings, for the first
time, this humble soldier is not
alone.
I don't see myself as a hero. Just
doing my job out there that day.
SCHOOL BELL RINGS
Next up - Palmerston North Boys'
High. The school has a proud
military past.
Many former pupils fought and lost
their lives during the two World
Wars.
We are absolutely honoured to be
visited by this delegation from the
SAS and Corporal Willie Apiata, VC.
He displays many of the qualities
dear to this school. His courage and
humility are an example to us all.
School stand. >
BOYS CHANT HAKA
This symbolic act of 1600 boys is
a heartfelt demonstration of the
groundswell of national pride.
And his companions are briefly
thrown into the world of
Willie Apiata, VC.
My gosh, you guys
make me feel special.
CO. There you go.
People are immensely proud
as a result of his decoration.
I'd like to introduce
you to my wife.
Kia ora.
It seems everyone wants a
moment with Willie Apiata.
Anywhere I go now, the garage or
corner dairy, people always come up
now. 'Hey, are you Willie Apiata?'
From playgrounds to parade ground,
Willie has brought much honour to
all ranks.
Soldiers out there are just so
proud. This is a big lift for the
NZ Defence Force as a whole.
MEN CHANT HAKA
For Willie, an emotional
trip is nearly at an end.
The last port of call is the
Infantry Battalion's 50th
celebrations,
where he is to present
a special gift.
APPLAUSE
It says, 'Corporal Willie Apiata,
VC - the 1st NZ Special Air Service
Group.'
APPLAUSE
To acknowledge what this really
means to us as a war-fighting
organisation,
putting aside the political
correctness, we're talking about
killing the Queen's enemies.
The example of close combat and
the requirement of the bond between
soldiers is timeless -
transcends the technology we
have. I thank you for this.
Soldiers fight for a reason. They
don't necessarily, in the heat of
battle, fight for Queen and country,
or anything other than the
man on their left and right.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
In Afghanistan, three NZSAS soldiers
were trapped behind a burning
vehicle,
their commander bleeding to death.
I know enough about med through the
unit to know that it was an arterial
bleed.
Attempts to reach the first
aid only drew more fire.
Their chances of survival
were disappearing fast.
Soon as a vehicle like that has some
type of fire, it turns itself into a
lead magnet.
BOOM!
GUNS FIRE
You could definitely see one of the
vehicles that had come up to support
us engaging quite hardcore.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
The vehicle was getting hit hard,
cos it was visible by the assault
force, which was only about...
probably 25m away.
Things intensified to... Just had a
feeling if we stayed any longer, we
wouldn't last much longer.
We would probably all have
come home in a box.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
Their rate of fire had increased
even more and that was when Willie
decided, 'We're outta here.'
Chucked him on my shoulder.
I said, 'Let's go, mate.'
Then we headed off back towards
where we knew our guys were.
It certainly never came into
anyone's mind that we'd ever
leave anyone behind.
Their only hope - run through the
firefight to the support vehicle.
You just keep going till you...
either go where you wanna go or
you get dropped.
Running up that hill...
the ground was on fire.
MACHINE GUNS FIRE
Tracer whipping through the air.
I didn't feel no weight at all.
Adrenalin pumping through your body,
just knowing you have to cover that
area to get him to safety.
I don't know how to really
explain it better, but...
you've got everything that you've
learnt from the moment you're born
up till that moment
flowing through your body,
trying to help you get out
of that situation alive.
Against unbelievable odds, Corporal
Willie Apiata made it unscathed
and delivered his wounded commander
to a waiting medic. But the battle
was far from over.
It's the end of the road trip,
and there's only one place
Willie Apiata wants to be.
It was what I've been waiting for,
eh - to come home, bring the medal
back to the unit.
Bring it back to the lads. And say
to them, 'Here, boys. This is for
us.'
Whoo. Hey, boys.
Hey, brothers.
How's it going, bro?
Willie. Congratulations.
Congratulations, man.
Thank you, bro. Buddy.
Hey, bro.
Cheers, there, brother.
< So good to be in
here with a beer.
All these real formal things that
we've been to - this is the only
place I can let my hair down, eh.
BELL DINGS
Just like to say is, just kia ora to
everybody here, eh. Kia ora koutou.
I am proud and honoured to wear this
VC. It was- I didn't ask for it.
It was bestowed upon me,
and what my thoughts are is, I carry
it for us bros - the lads who were
there that day,
the lads that are here now, the ones
that are past and the ones that are
in the future.
Bros, it's so grounding to come home
because you fellas are my levellers.
You will always keep me the same.
And that's how I wanna be,
one of the lads with you fellas.
So, tena koutou, tena koutou,
tena koutou katoa.
Cheers, brothers.
GLASSES CLINK